Mss.Ms.Coll.76.17
American Philosophical Society
- Subseries E. Printed Materials, 1911-1962; 1.0 item
  - Subsubseries 3 - US Military, 1911, 1916, 1917, 1939, undated
    - Instruction Pamphlet for Gunner's Examination in the Field Artillery, Service Schools Bulletin No. 6, undated; 1.0 item
      Brooklyn: Second FIeld Artillery, N.G.N.Y.
    - Official History of the Militia and the National Guard of the State of Pennsylvania, 1939; 1.0 item
      20th Anniversary Edition booklet special issue dedicated to Major General WM. G. Price, Jr and the 28th Division. Bookmark on page commemorating Henry Howard Houston II.
      Compiled and Published by Colonel Charles J. Hendler. Philadelphia, PA. December 1939.
    - Price, William Gray. Activities and Citations of the 53rd Field Artillery Brigade 28th Division United States Army: World War, 1914-1918, 1919; 1.0 item
      Pamphlet describing the activities and citations of the 53rd Field Artillery Brigade.
      Chester, PA: Press of Chester Times, 1919. Print.
    - The Service and its Insignia, 1917; 1.0 item
      Philadelphia: Bailey, Banks & Biddle Company. 1917.
      A small pamphlet detailing the various signs, symbols, and insignia of the United States Armed Forces.
    - Drill regulations for Field Artillery, 1911; 1.0 item; United States. War Dept.
      Henry Howard Houston II's copy of drill regulations for horse and light field artillery in the United States Army.
      Washington, Govt. Print. Off., 1911.
  - Subsubseries 4 - University of Pennsylvania, 1916-1918
    This subsub-series of Printed Materials contains published works relating to the University of Pennsylvania and the Zeta Psi fraternity, of which Henry Howard Houston II was a member.
    - 160th Commencement pamphlet, 1916 June 21; 1.0 item; University of Pennsylvania
      Brochure for the 160th commencement ceremony.
    - Alumni Register, June 1917 & November 1918; 1.0 item; University of Pennsylvania. General Alumni Society
      Two editions of the monthly alumni register published by the General Alumni Society.
    - The Pennsylvania Gazette, 1924 December 19; 1.0 item; University of Pennsylvania
      This edition of the PA Gazette has an article on page 252 about the Houston Cup given to the UPenn soccer team in memory of Henry Howard Houston II who was a member of the team while a student at the University of Pennsylvania.
      Published by the University of Pennsylvania.
    - Fraternity House Photographs, unknown; 1.0 item
      Interior and exterior photographs of the Zeta Psi fraternity house at the intersection of 33rd and Walnut streets in Philadelphia, PA.
      Zeta Psi Fraternity. Sigma Chapter.
    - Sigma Zetes doing their bit, 1917 November 1; 1.0 item; Zeta Psi Fraternity. Sigma Chapter.
      Broadside from Sigma chapter of Zeta Psi fraternity at University of Pennsylvania with list of fraternity alumni in service during the war. Henry Howard Houston II is listed approximately 1/3 of the way down the right hand column.
    - The Circle of Zeta Psi, 1918 November; 1.0 item; Zeta Psi Fraternity. Sigma Chapter.
      National newsletter for Zeta Psi fraternity. Article of Henry Howard Houston II and his death on pages 57-58.
  - Subsubseries 5 - Newspaper Clippings, 1917-1936, 1962
    This subsub-series of Printed Materials is comprised of newspaper clippings, many of which are related to Henry Howard Houston II's death, the anniversary of his death, or the role of artillery during World War I. Because these materials are oversize, they are located in an oversize box separate from the other Printed Materials.
    - From Sam Houston to Henry Howard Houston II, July 1918 and unknown; 1.0 item
      One pouch contains newspaper clippings that were loosely mixed in with some correspondence between Sam and Henry Houston. All of them pertain to the war.
    - Sky Spies, September 28, 1962; 1.0 item
      A brief newspaper article about artillery spotters in balloons during World War I.
    - Miscellaneous Newspapers, 1918-1936; 1.0 item
      Three large folders of newspapers, newsletters,and pamphlets spanning the years 1918 to 1936.Includes a large full page article about Henry Howard Houston II from the Germantown Independent Gazette Aug 18, 1921.
- Subseries F. Graphics, 1914-1918, unknown
  The Graphics sub-series consistes of large, mid-size, and small photographs. Most of these photographs capture Henry’s surroundings during the time he served in the armed forces. Therefore, a large portion depict France during World War I, and some may depict his surroundings during his training period (Fort Sill, Oklahoma; the Texas-Mexico border). They show the everyday life of a World War I soldier and, from the stark images of bombed out buildings, the ravages of war itself.
  For each photo or group of photos, we made an educated estimate of the most prominent location or person depicted in the photo. We then arranged the photos alphabetically based on the first letter of that prominent noun. For example, "B" for "Bombed Building," "H" for "Henry Howard Houston, II," and "F" for "France." Where the location was unknown and there was no date, those photos were categorized under "U" for "Undated."
  - Arc de Triomphe, Print, 1919
  - Aerial Photograph, French Regions
  - Bombed Building, before and after, undated
  - Cathedrale de Reims, Print, undated
  - Cathedrale de St.-Jean - La Somme, France - Print, undated
  - Enumerated Description of Photographs, undated
    It is unclear to which photographs this list corresponds. However, the photos would be from Henry's time in the armed service.
  - France, small photographs, 1916, undated
  - France, small photographs, 1918, undated
  - France, mid and small-sized photographs, 1917-1918, undated
  - French Battlescene Postcards, unsent, 1914-1921, undated
  - French Battlefield Photos, 1917-1918
  - Houston, Henry Howard II and Ambulance Trucks, Folder I, 1917-1918
  - Houston, Henry Howard II and Ambulance Trucks, Folder 2, 1917-1918
  - Houston, Henry Howard II and Ambulance Trucks, Folder 3, 1917-1918
  - Houston, Henry Howard II and Ambulance Trucks, Folder 4, 1917-1918
  - Houston, Henry Howard II and Ambulance Trucks, Folder 5, 1917-1918
  - Houston, Henry Howard II and Ambulance Trucks, Folder 6, 1917-1918
  - Houston, Henry Howard II - Boat to France, undated
  - Houston, Henry Howard II and Brother, Childhood, undated
  - Houston, Henry Howard II, Childhood Album, unknown
    This large leather album chronicles Henry's childhood and teenage years with many photographs. It is oversize.
    Original order was preserved in this album.
  - Houston, Henry Howard II - Mexico, undated
  - Houston, Henry Howard II - Military Portraits, Oversize
    This oversize blue box contains a negative print press from which Henry's image was imprinted, two military portraits of Henry, a small leather album of Henry while he was in the service, and oversize photos of Henry in the army and at Penn.
  - Houston, Henry Howard II - Portrait Photographs, undated
  - Houston, Henry Howard II - Postcards - Friends, undated
  - Houston, Henry Howard II - S.S.U. #12 - Group Photo, 1917 January
  - Maison de Jeanne d'Arc - Domzeny - France, Print, undated
  - Marais sur le front americain, Print, undated
  - "Pour Madame Houston" Postcards, undated
  - Small Photos and Accompanying Enumerated Descriptive List
    The list in Henry's handwriting has numbers paired with descriptions that correspond to the numbers on the back of each photo.
  - Unknown Persons and Buildings, undated
    On the back of each photo are numbers that may correspond to the numbers and descriptions in the "Enumerated Description of Photographs" list.
  - Unknown Persons and Building, undated
  - Unknown Persons and Building, undated
- Subseries G. Maps, 1914-1918
  The Maps are not arranged in alphabetical order, but in accordance with the size of each map with a view to protect and preserve the material. A Rand McNally map of the western front battle lines of 1914 and 1918 is located in Subseries D - Bound Volumes, due to its smaller physical size.
  These Maps are located in the Oversize section of the collection. The Maps sub-series consists of very large maps of western Europe, France, and specific French regions. A couple maps have Henry’s name written on the back in pencil.
  - Maps of France - Oversized folder, 1914-1918
    Maps
    One oversized folder contains: -One small map of the area surrounding Ypres that shows the approximate lines of advance for the Battle of Ypres. Dated November 6, 1917 - April 29, 1918. -One large map of Reims and the surrounding area in great detail. -One large map of Meaux(?), France. "Meaux" is written in pencil on the back. -One large map of Soissons. "H H Houston" written in pencil on the back. -One large map of the Region Laon-Soissons. "H H Houston" written in pencil on the back.
    Maps; World War I -- France; World War, 1914-1918
- Subseries H. Realia
  The Realia sub-series consists of large to small cultural artifacts. Of significance are (a) ambulance armbands in white with a red cross which Henry, as an ambulance driver, may have worn; and (b) a “US Army” sewn lapel which Henry may have worn.
  The Realia were arranged with three goals in mind: (a) to keep artifacts which accompanied each other together; (b) to keep objects of like size together; and (c) to protect fragile items.
  - Realia Box 1 - Keys, Lock, Bullet, Metal Pellet
    Box Contents
    -Three small metal keys -One large iron key -One small lock -One large bullet -One small metal pellet/ball
  - Realia Box 2 - Linen handkerchief and oil painting on wood
    -One small white linen handkerchief with blue letter "P" and red letters "A" and "F" embroidered on it. -An oil painting of a cemetery on a piece of wood.
  - Realia Box 3 - Flag and Handkerchief
    -One large white linen handkerchief with "Henry Houston" embroidered on it. date 1899. -One large red linen flag with a white five point star sewn into the center.
  - Realia Box 4 - Decorative Asian Handkerchief, Pocket Square Purse, Bowtie, Ambulance Armband, Armband with Numbers and Red Cord.
    -One purse made of a fragile purple cloth with flags (USA, Romania, France, Japan, Belgium). -One decorative handkerchief with asian theme. -Armband with numbers "87" and a red cord. -Ambulance armband (red cross on white background) -Various striped, colored ribbons
  - Realia Box 5 - War Related Realia
    - One large black leather wallet, with the yellow inscription "H. H. Houston, Philadelphia" inscribed - One thermometer encased in a blue box - Two shells welded together as a curiousity - A box which had contained Philadelphia soil. An inscription states that this soil had been placed on Henry's grave in Suresnes, France. - One small beaded ring which depicts the ambulance cross (white, with a red cross in the center).
  - Realia Box 6 - Miscellaneous realia
    -Two felt bicentennial armbands with years 1740 and 1940 -Ticket stub for transportation between El Paso and Tobin, Texas -Unknown containter lid with condolences for Henry Howard Houston II's death -Henry Howard Houston II's money: 4x $1 silver bank notes from 1899 and 1x 1904 gold $5 coin. -A toy airplane made from a bullet -Dried Flowers removed from bottom of larger storage box that came with accession of manuscript collection. -One Unites States Army Badge -One cloth ambulance armband -One fabric cord -One pencil sharpened by Henry Howard Houston II